# Meena Devii Muralikumar

### Research Statement

My research interests are broadly in the intersection of Human-Computer Interaction and Artificial Intelligence/Machine Learning. I study if and how AI/ML algorithms are human-centered and challenges involved in using them as design material. I seek to bridge knowledge gaps for non-experts of AI/ML, especially designers and UX practitioners, and develop solutions for better engagement with AI/ML algorithms during the design process.

#### Education

2019 - current University of Washington, Seattle, PhD, Human Centered Design and

Engineering, GPA: 3.95/4.0. Advised by Prof. David McDonald

2017-2019 University of California, Irvine, MS, Informatics, GPA: 3.96/4.0.

2011-2015 **Amrita Vishwa Vidyapeetham**, *BTech, Computer Science and Engineering*, GPA: 9.3/10.0.

## Academic Research Experience

2020 - current **Research Assistant**, *Social Computational Systems Lab*, *HCDE*, *UW*, Seattle, WA.

- Conducted a pilot study using surveys to evaluate the performance of the machine learning model, Perspective, to detect toxicity in online comments from social media websites
- Leading the subsequent large-scale study based on the pilot under Dr. David McDonald's guidance
- 2019 **Research Assistant**, Emerging Capacities of Mass Participation Laboratory, HCDE, UW, Seattle, WA.
  - Analyzed interview data from journalists working on the online misinformation and disinformation beat and synthesized findings under the supervision of PhD student Melinda Haughey

- 2019 **Research Assistant**, Human-Centered Data Science Lab, HCDE, UW, Seattle, WA.
  - Analyzed online fan fiction data using quantitative methods and created visualizations under the supervision of Dr. Aragon and PhD student Jenna Frens

#### 2018-2019 **Research Assistant**, Evoke Lab, Informatics, UCI, Irvine, CA.

- o Conducted an experimental pilot study under Dr. Matthew Bietz's supervision to investigate if visualizations could help users understand algorithms in Twitter
- Developed a mock-up of Twitter's interface and algorithm and used D3.js visualizations for the experimental condition
- Published findings as a poster at ACM CSCW 2019

#### 2018–2019 **Research Assistant**, *Transformative Play Lab*, *Informatics*, *UCI*, Irvine, CA.

 Designed, developed, and evaluated a narrative Virtual Reality experience based on an original theatrical musical under the supervision of Dr. Tess Tanenbaum

#### 2018 **Research Assistant**, Evoke Lab, Informatics, UCI, Irvine, CA.

- Designed and executed a qualitative study to understand and support user motivations for online donations to charities, along with a team of 4 Master's students under the guidance of Dr. Matthew Bietz
- Conducted competitive analysis and semi-structured interviews as part of the study
- Analyzed interview data using affinity diagrams and derived themes
- o Devised persuasive design patterns for charity websites that augment user's intrinsic motivation to donate

### **Publications**

# **Proceedings**

- Conference Saumya Gupta, Theresa Jean Tanenbaum, Meena Devii Muralikumar, and Aparajita S. Marathe. 2020. Investigating Roleplaying and Identity Transformation in a Virtual Reality Narrative Experience. In Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, 1–13. DOI:https://doi.org/10.1145/3313831.3376762
  - Posters Meena Devii Muralikumar and Matthew J. Bietz. 2019. Visualizing Algorithmic Selection in Social Media. In Conference Companion Publication of the 2019 on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW '19). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, 319–323. DOI:https://doi.org/10.1145/3311957.3359476

# Proceedings

Workshop • Meena Devii Muralikumar and Bonnie Nardi. 2018. Addressing limits through tracking food. In Proceedings of the 2018 Workshop on Computing within Limits (LIMITS '18). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, Article 3, 1–9 DOI:https://doi.org/10.1145/3232617.3232620

## Academic Teaching Experience

2020 **Teaching Assistant**, *HCDE*, *UW*, Seattle, WA.

o Summer 2020 - HCDE 598. Designing for Virtual Reality

2018–2019 **Teaching Assistant**, *Informatics, UCI*, Irvine, CA.

- o Spring 2019 IN4MATX 191B. Senior Design Project
- o Winter 2019 IN4MATX 191A. Senior Design Project
- o Fall 2018 IN4MATX 125. Computer Game Development
- Spring 2018 IC SCI 60. Computer Games and Society
- Winter 2018 IN4MATX 131. Introduction to Human Computer Interaction

#### Skills

Research User Interviews, Contextual Inquiry, Surveys, Experimental Design, A/B Testing, Statistical analyses, Personas, Card Sorting, Affinity Diagramming

Coding Python, PyTorch, Java, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, php, R

### Service

2020 Associate Chair (AC) - ACM CHI, Late Breaking Work

- As 1AC, recruited external reviewers, wrote meta-reviews, and made recommendations as to whether the LBW should be accepted to CHI 2020
- Completed additional reviews as 2AC.

## Industry Experience

2015–2017 Software Engineer II, ThermoFisher Scientific, Bangalore, India.

- Developed secure, scalable micro-services using Amazon Web Services
- Contributed to UI/UX development by developing Javascript SDKs and user interfaces
- Spot Award for UI development contribution
- o Actively contributed to and led sprint, agile activities for the team